People think the Slackware installation
is very hard but it's easy
the "complicated" part is in the post-installation
where the user will need read
(Long Live Slackware...)
The Slackware Project started when Patrick was student in Minnesota State University Moorhead
and he was looking for a Lisp interpreter
that's when he found in a GNU/Linux distribution called SLS, Softlanding Linux System
He then started using this system daily
to understand better about this new system,
about this new undiscovered world at this time
then he found various bugs in this
distribuition, SLS, and begin fix it
in a short time he did more fixes than SLS project
they taken all patches,
all fixes and send to SLS project
they not implemented the fixes
then, I think he was a little revolted
he made the decision to provide this project
and will be called Slackware
17th of July, 1993, around midnight and sixteen
they make first version of
Slackware project available via FTP
the SLS was a first generation distribution
Slackware we can say was the second generation distribution
so it was not from the first delivery, since it was already based on that moment
but is a distribution with a recognized name
as it is also the oldest distribution still in development, to the present day
(For what purpose can Slackware be used?)
For several, since use in a server because Slackware is very stable
Slackware carries the trust of being a very stable distribution
like a rock, solid as a rock
can also be used in a common desktop
for daily use
I like several people in the world
use Slackware distribution as their primary operating system
and can also be a distribution for academic use
to use in colleges or even at home, anyway ...
for you to study the system
Of course there are many things nowadays in the others distributions
that were evolving and Slackware left behind
Slackware was not following all the technology that we have today in GNU/Linux
it left a lot behind things like PAM, SystemD and others
but you learn how to setup the whole system in text mode
so there's no cute interface to click on
you just open any notep... no notepad (hehe)
You just open any text editor and can edit in its most
so it is very interesting for academic use as well
(What philosophy do Slackware follow?)
Slackware has a philosophy called KISS, Keep It Simple Stupid
This philosophy was created in the US Navy, 1960
And it aims to keep things simple as possible
discarding what you do not need
So Slackware follows this same pattern, that same philosophy
You can see the Slackware installer, it uses a Dialog
a box, which looks like the 80's or 90's, a very old box
since the beginning it uses the same installer
and that is simple
You in a few ...
few keystrokes, you'll be able to easily install Slackware
So it follow this philosophy to keep as simple as possible
(Is the official ISO on the Slackware website outdated?)
As you enter the Slackware site the novices, beginners, who are starting on the system
they look at ISO there 14.2 released in 2016
everyone looks, "Dammit, this is very outdated"
but in fact the version available is the stable version
Slackware works with two principles, two categories
Packages, can I say so
one is stable version, which you can use on a server
or common use too
but in an older version
and it only receives security updates for the system
only security patches
While we have another version
called current
which is updated every day
every day has updated to Slackware in the current version
This version is not so stable
It may break because it is a development version
as the name says current
So there are updates almost every day
Unfortunately this version does not have a download on the official website
but we can find on AlienBOB's website which I can say he is Patrick right-hand
You have on his site a current version that you can download
and enjoy the latest version
It is in development, for example in version 14.2 stable downloaded from official site
still with KDE 4 while the current is with KDE 5 Plasma, understand?
So there are a lot of cool updates
you can take a look
If you downloaded the stable version you can go there in mirrors
located in /etc/slackpkg/mirrors
You can go there change the mirror and switch to current version too
you can upgrade the system to the current version
but I do not recommend that version if you need a totally stable environment
this version as I said, it is "stable" but not so much as the stable version
So no, Slackware is not outdated
and it's being updated daily
Patrick has been doing an excellent job for years, years and years
(Is Slackware totally free software?)
in terms it is and is not
there are many softwares with license compatible with the Free Software Foundation
but also has proprietary software
so it's not a project 100% free software
if you access the FSF you will have something like, "Which distributions we do not support"
and Slackware is on this list
it has proprietary software called xv present inside it by default
you can remove it on installation but it is there by default
There are other things in the extras like Google Chrome and others, Mozilla Firefox itself
as we know it accepts plugins and that are not free software
and this goes against this question
If you want a distribution 100% free software
by default it is not 100% free software
but you can make it 100% free software
I have articles and videos teaching how to make Slackware 100% free software
only free software
We have a distribution that is derived of Slackware
they do not change anything they only remove all software that is not free
xv and among others
they created their own repository and is called Freenix the old FreeSlack
so they have a Slackware 100% free software
but also can make Slackware 100% free software with a little trick of magic
very cool
(Why does Slackware have few official packages?)
Yes, Slackware has a few packages by default and if you open the Slackware's ISO
we will find the whole Slackware repository around more than a thousand packages
is present in Slackware's ISO
So there really are few packages
but when you do a full install of Slackware it will serve you very well
it gets complicated when you want to install other things
that's where the SlackBuilds project comes in
The community created SlackBuilds project
which are recipes, like food recipes
are recipes written in shell script
are recipes that you will compile
a software, make copies and much more
they do not include the program source, include only those scripts and information that you will need
at this time I use Slackware, since 2008
SlackBuilds serve me very well and I never had any problems
"ohh, I did not find this software there X or Y"
I always found software using
SlackBuilds. It's very complete
so it's from the source, you'll have to compile it when use SlackBuilds
You can contribute
you can contribute, if you know how to programming a little in shell script
you can contribute to the SlackBuilds project
creating your recipes for the project
and it will help a lot of people
The biggest software I have there in present date is DokuWiki
is like a Wikipedia created in PHP
and I'm the maintainer of this script, this recipe to use DokuWiki
so you will not get stuck only in official packages
we also have the SlackOnly website. Which provides pre-compiled packages
you just go there and do installpkg
to install this package
so there's SlackOnly
have many softwares for Slackware
there is much that you can enjoy
SlackBuilds and SlackOnly are the
ones I recommend for Slackware users
(Does Slackware have a package manager?)
Users starting in Slackware
they get lost a lot in this issue of package management
there are a lot of misinformation on the internet
that says Slackware does not have a package manager, that's a lie
it does have a low-level package manager called pkgtools
which are a lot of tools,
made in shell script
has the installpkg to install packages,
removepkg to remove packages
upgradepkg to update packages
we have makepkg to create a package
has a low-level manager
with what you need
around year of 2008 was inserted from the extra
a script also in shell, called slackpkg
created by a Brazilian, Piter Punk
a hug for him <3
and this script aims to update the system's packages,
upgrade, install, do all this
So we can even put slackpkg as a high-level package manager
but also does not solve dependencies
so we have the low-level package manager
pkgtools, which does not resolve dependencies
and the slackpkg that we can call high-level package manager, that also does not resolve dependencies
but we have these package managers
The people be afraid but there's nothing to be afraid
it's easy just follow the lot of information and documentation available on the internet
or go on a slackware IRC channel
You'll ask your question and the guys will answer you
the Slackware community is very kind
for sure they will always help
(Can a newbie use Slackware?)
The newbie user coming from an easier distribution
such as Linux Mint
where they give you the interface ready, "use this interface because this distribution is for this"
they will have some "problems" in Slackware
but nothing that a good reading does not solve
That's a cool thing about Slackware. "Get this book or get this documentation and read"
read so you can use
and the name of the project already says this
slack that is slack and ware that is ware
(not make sense in english)
so, the system does nothing for you the administrator is who does
the administrator is who will have to take on of administering the system
the newbie user who never used terminal in his/her life
will have a little difficulty but nothing that a good reading does not solve
or a little search
everybody already was newbie
I was a newbie too, everyone was already
we got used to the system
and the power it gives you ... administrative, is very good
(In case of fatality can the project stop?)
For who do not know he (Patrick) already had two health problems
the project paused at this time
but then continued normally
so when a problem occurs
the project will continue
we have a very strong community a close-knit community
We have Patrick right-hands men
the AlienBOB, does much for the project
We have Workman too he does a lot for the project
we have these guys and for sure they will keep the project active
of course because it is an almost personal project
where Patrick decides what happens or not in the distribution
there's a lot of him in the project
What we see in Slackware project is a lot of Patrick's vision
What will happen when someone else maintains the project?
I do not know how it will be or if the community will maintain it. I do not know
will have a little of the vision of that person too
it may be that the person wants to change but the community will not allow
"Oops, let's keep the project objective"
this is what happened to the Debian project
Ian Murdock was the founder of the Debian project
died and the project continued
nowadays the Debian project is as strong as ever
so the same will happen with the Slackware project
something happened with Patrick? OK, but the project will continue this project can not die
it's a historical project
(Is Slackware's website outdated?)
who access the Slackware project website which is slackware.com
users are accustomed to this design of the 2000s
They look and say, "Jesus, why is it so old?"
They still use frames on the site
but the purpose of the site such as the project philosophy itself, KISS philosophy
which is to keep as simple as possible
he kept it, it's serving, it's working, it's okay
older users use Links or Lynx
terminal browser
they browsing there and when you enter the Slackware website... you can test there
use the Links and the URL which is www.slackware.com
you will see that navigation is perfect when using Links
you can do everything there and much faster than clicking on a browser
such as Google Chrome, Firefox, IceCat, anyway
so it's much simpler and easier using this text mode browser
formerly we had to make a mess
there was slackpkg in the extras but not everyone who used it. So what we did?
we went there in the Slackware changelog, watched what was updated, what needed to be updated
We would go in any mirror and download it
we opened two terminals compared and downloaded them
compare the version with of the system
"Oh, you have to upgrade", so we used the D key on Links and downloaded into a directory
then all packages were within this directory
then we do an upgradepkg *.t?z
where "?" means any character
or just tgz or txz, anyway
enter key and all packages were updated, simple as well
there are people who still do it
I myself did this a lot
nowadays I use slackpkg for convenience and to be more practical too
certainty the idea, "if it is working correctly, there is no reason to change"
also serves for those people who use a text mode browser
for sure stayed that way because of it too
(The first package manager in the Linux history?)
The fact that few people know
is that Slackware had the honor of having the first package manager in the Linux world
launched in 1994, 93/94
came before dpkg, before the rpm, came before all those
they was the first package manager in the Linux history
formerly on Unix or even in the early generations of Linux distributions
it was all done in the compilation everything manually
you had read the README what all SlackUser does and people who compile
read the README, see what is the step by step, what you have to follow
then by the terminal in practice of course had to make some adjustments to run
do this configuration manually to do a build
the package manager came to do that
Patrick had this vision
"let's pile up all the compiled put it together in one place and pack it"
the Slackware package is just a compressed little tar
xz or gz (which is gzip) and let's pack that
Let's pack everything you need in one place
then we will do what?
we extract it to the root of the user, then remove
the Slackware package manager are shell scripts
very easy to use
and the person can help resolve bugs in those scripts.
Very cool, that's the coolest
(Does the project use some kind of public versioning system?)
we see these projects more "fad"
they use a lot of versioning like Git for example, which is very famous
and Slackware does not follow this pattern it's a more closed development where Patrick does it all
in the view of an ordinary person who is not in the development
This happens to no one intruding
when we put in the github or notabug, anyway
people will wanting to help and that's good but each person will want to do it in your own way
it is normal and good, the freedom that we have
but that is bad for a project that has a philosophy and follows a pattern
e.g. "Hey, let's add SystemD, let's add a PAM"
What is impractical for the project, many people are intruding, "let's do it, let's do that"
and it ends up not working
so Slackware does not have public versioning
(Marketing Play? From version 4 to 7...)
One historical fact is when Slackware jumped from version 4.0 to 7.0
in the 1990s the Slackware project was heavily used
but his version implied that the project was out of date
while the other distributions were in version 5, version 6, Slackware was in version 4, for example
Patrick made a marketing move
"Let's jump from version 4 to version 7 to show the people that we are updated like these other distributions"
so it was a marketing move, it did not change much to skip 3 versions
really was a marketing move.
(What do you expect from the project?)
I hope the Slackware project has many years of road
And that people come to know the project
and not reading these things on the internet that others speak
"it is an outdated project, not every user can use it", this is a lie
Slackware is there for your daily use, on your server
and will do very well with learning too
you will learn, much, really much using the Slackware Linux distribution
so, that's it
Thanks, thank you for the opportunity!
(This work is licensed under CC BY 4.0 license)